Berard Haile papers, 1893-1961 (bulk 1925-1961)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Berard Haile papers, 1893-1961 (bulk 1925-1961)
AZ 132
Haile, Berard, 1874-1961
Correspondence, manuscripts of published and unpublished works, notes, drawings, notebooks, sermons, prayers, and historical accounts relate to Haile's study of Navajo ceremonials and the Navajo language. Includes correspondence with church officials and anthropologists; manuscripts, notes, and drawings related to Navajo language, culture and ceremonials; interlinear Navajo-English notebooks; accounts of the founding and early history of the Lukachukai and St. Michaels Missions; and sermons, prayers, etc. from Haile's teaching in these missions.
16.25 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Franciscan missionary, linguist, and anthropologist. Worked extensively with the Navajo at Lukachukai and St. Michaels Missions in Arizona and wrote several works on Navajo ceremonials, language and grammar.
Organization
This collection is organized into fourteen series:
Series I. Personal Material
Series II. Correspondence
Series III.Christian Teachings
Series IV.Navajo Culture
Series V. Government Relations; Interpreters' Institute
Series VI.Stories and Legends
Series VII. Miscellaneous
Series VIII. Ceremonials
Series IX. Reprints Pertaining to the Navajo
Series X. Navajo Language and Grammar
Series XI. Original Drawings and Two Drafts of the Emergence Myth
Series XII. Linguistic Notes (Navajo)
Series XIII. Index to Notes for BLESSINGWAY
Sand Paintings
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, manuscripts of published and unpublished works, notes, drawings, notebooks, sermons, prayers, and historical accounts relate to Haile's study of Navajo ceremonials and the Navajo language. Includes correspondence with church officials and anthropologists; manuscripts, notes, and drawings related to Navajo language, culture and ceremonials; interlinear Navajo-English notebooks; accounts of the founding and early history of the Lukachukai and St. Michaels Missions; and sermons, prayers, etc. from Haile's teaching in these missions. Also present is material from the Interpreters' Institute at Fort Wingate, New Mexico, 1935; the Navajo constitution and related papers; reprints of articles by other authors about the Navajo; and related material on Apache and Zuni Indians. Selected correspondents include Gladys Reichard, Edward Sapir, Clyde Kluckhohn, Anselm Weber, and Leopold Ostermann, as well as government officials, missionary organizations, and Navajo individuals.
Access Terms
Haile, Berard, 1874-1961
Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
Weber, Anslem, 1862-1921
Ostermann, Leopold
Kluckhohn, Clyde, 1905-1960
Reichard, Gladys Amanda, 1893-1955
Interpreters' Institute (Ft. Wingate, N.M.)
Franciscans -- Missions -- Arizona
St. Michaels Mission (Ariz.) -- History
Lukachukai Mission (Ariz.) -- History
Navajo Indians -- Religion
Navajo Indians -- Rites and ceremonies
Missionaries -- Arizona -- Archives
Navajo language -- Texts
Zuni Indians -- Rites and ceremonies
Apache Indians -- Rites and ceremonies
Missions -- Arizona -- History
Sandpaintings
Navajo Indians -- Government relations
Catholic Church -- Missions -- Arizona
Navajo language -- Dictionaries -- English
Navajo Indians -- Folklore
Navajo Indians -- Missions
Navajo mythology
Manuscripts for publication
Correspondence
Notes
Drawings
Container List
- Series I: Personal Material
  - Biographical material (General, misc.). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical material (Honors, awards, memberships). (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diaries. 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bibliographies. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Book Reviews by Father Berard. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Book Revies of Father Berard's Publications. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Books in Father Berard's Library. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Class Notes; Notes on Reading. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Course in Harmony. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Misc. Financial Records. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Missionary Work. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lukachukai Mission (St. Isabel's). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - St. Michaels Mission. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Typewriter Manuel and Correspondence. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous and General. 1902-1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous and General. 1902-1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous and General. 1902-1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous and General. 1902-1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous and General. 1902-1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous and General. 1902-1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Family (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Donovan, Joseph P. 1945-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hayden, Carl. 1919, 1924, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Littell, Norman M. 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Riordan, T.A. and M.J. 1919, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sandoval, Albert. 1922-1944 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Shiya, Thomas S. 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Father Anslem Weber. 1910-1916 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Father Leopold Ostermann. 1903-1925? (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Father Marcellus Troester. 1917-1929 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Culin, Stewart and An Ethnologic Dictionary of the Navajo Language. 1907-1929 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cushing, Archbishop Richard J. 1943-1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Gusinde, Martin. 1929-1930, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Various Church Officials. 1902-1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Various Church Officials. 1902-1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Various Church Officials. 1902-1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Various Church Officials. 1902-1958 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bureau of Catholic Indian Missions (William H. Ketchum, William Hughes, Charles Lusk). 1902-1935 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Franciscan Missionaries of Mary. 1942-1954 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Franciscan Indian Mission Aid. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Red Rock Presbyterian Hospital Protest. 1920 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Goddard, Pliny E. 1924-1929 (Box 3a, Folder 1)
  - Herzog, George. 1934-1936 (Box 3a, Folder 2)
  - Hodge, F.W. 1910-1945 (Box 3a, Folder 3)
  - Kluckhohn, Clyde. 1932-1958 (Box 3a, Folder 4)
  - Reichard, Gladys. 1925-1939 (Box 3a, Folder 5)
  - Sapir, Edward. 1929-1939 (Box 3a, Folder 6)
  - Sapir, Edward. 1929-1939 (Box 3a, Folder 7)
  - Sapir, Edward. 1929-1939 (Box 3a, Folder 8)
  - Spier, Leslie. 1937-1938 (Box 3a, Folder 9)
  - Van Valkenburgh, Richard. 1942-1954 (Box 3a, Folder 10)
  - Wyman, Leland C. 1943-1957 (Box 3a, Folder 11)
  - University of Chicago (Fay-Cooper Cole, Fred Eggan, Henry Hoijer, Robert Redfield, and David Stevens of the Rockefeller Foundation). 1929-1961 (Box 3a, Folder 12)
  - Catholic Anthropolgical Conference. 1926-1932 (Box 3a, Folder 13)
- Series: III Christian Teachings (in English and Navajo)
  - Cathechisms. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Commandments. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gospels. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Prayers. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Proper of the Saints. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Sermons by Father Berard. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Sermons by Father Berard. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sermons, prayers, hymns, etc. by others. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Way of the Cross. By Quentin Hauer. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous notes and discourses on various aspects of the Catholic faith, including the sacraments, confession, sin, confirmation, etc. Discourse on the visit of the Bishop. Funeral oration for Chee Dodge. Funeral oration for Father Marcellus Troester. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series IV: Navajo Culture
  - Navajo life (general and miscellaneous). (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Basketry. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Cosmos (universe, time, direction, elements, etc). (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Education; schools. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Fabrics. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Family relationships; clans. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Games. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Hogan. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Land. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Law and crime; morality; ethics. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Moccasin making. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Place names. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Plants. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Prayersticks. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - "Property Concepts of the Navaho Indians." (Published 1954) Various drafts and notes, as well as typescripts of the 1929 and 1948 versions. 1929, 1948, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Religion (general). (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Soul, Concepts of. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Starlore and masks. (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Series V: Government Relations; Interpreters' Institute, 1935
  - Correspondence, U.S. Dept. of the Interior. 1934-1937 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Interpreters' Institute: General papers, ballot, questions & answers, directives, terms & phrases, etc. 1935 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Interpreters' Institute: General papers, ballot, questions & answers, directives, terms & phrases, etc. 1935 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Indian Reorganization Act; Wheeler-Howard Act. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Navajo Constitution. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Code of Laws, under the Constitution. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Navajo Tribal Council Reorganization. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Navajo Tribal Council By-laws, etc. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Government Officials (Navajo trans.). (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Government documents. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Navajo newspaper. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Grazing regulations. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Roundrock Incident (Holograph ms. by Navajo-who-killed-his-story; typescript with notes, etc. English and Navajo). 1893 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Series VI: Stories and Legends
  - Seventeen holograph interlinear notebooks. (Box 7)
  - Notebook containing typescripts, with holograph versions laid in, of various animal stories. (Box 8)
  - Typescript of "Bead Way." (original) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of "Changing Bear Maiden." (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Typescript of "Pertaining to the Creating of Game" and "Pertaining to One Who Changed into a Doe." (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of "Raised by the Owl." (carbon of completed ms., typescript interlinear, holograph interlinear, and notes) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Typescript of "Where People Moved Opposite Each Other." (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Typescript of "Coyote Stories." (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Typescript of "Coyote Way." (carbon) (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Typescript of "The Wardance Ceremony." (original) (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Series VII: Miscellaneous
  - "Navaho Residence North of the San Juan River" by Richard Van Valkenburgh, Typescript. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "Notes of the Franciscan Missions in Northwestern New Mexico." Holograph ms. and typescript. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Notes on the Zuni Indians." (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "Beardance, a ceremony of the Jicarilla Apache." Typescript (carbon). Published, in slightly altered form, in Beautyway, ed. by Leland C. Wyman, Pantheon. 1957 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Head and Face Masks in Navaho Ceremonialism. Holograh notebook, and drawings. Published by St. Michaels Press. 1942 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Navaho Sacrificial Figurines. Holograph notebook (text): "Figurines and Prayersticks; special ceremonies outside of regular chants." Published by Univ. of Chicago Press. Also: original drawings and book distribution list. 1947 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "A Meeting with D.M. Riordan." Holograph ms. in English and Navajo. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - "Reading," by Little Singer. Holograph ms.; interlinear typescript. 1937 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "Origin of Order of Naat'oi Ba ka." Typescript (carbon) and holograph items. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "Navaho Land." Typescript (orginal). (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - "The Navaho Land Question." Typescript (original) versions, holograph additions and corrections. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Holograph ms., of which an altered version was published in Navaho Texts by E. Sapir as "A Navaho's Historical Reminiscences." (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Four holograph interlinear notebooks, mostly materials supplied by Charlie Mitchell, and published by the Linguistic Society of America, 1942, in Navaho Texts, by Edward Sapir. (Box 10)
  - Four holograph interlinear notebooks in wrapper labeled "Misc. Crystal." (Box 10)
  - Three holograph notebooks in Navaho (two marked "Clans"; one possibly related to Blessingway, according to Leland C. Wyman. June 1964 (Box 10)
  - Typescript (carbon) on Hopi Snake Dance. (Box 10)
  - Holograph ms. and typescript regarding Narbona. (Box 10)
  - Two incomplete typescripts (carbons) regarding Navaho religious artifacts. (Box 10)
  - Six items in Navaho (typescript and holograph), one identified as "War Reminiscences" and another "1st Wagons Issued." (Box 10)
  - Notes on "fumigation," burning, incense, etc. in relation to ceremonials. (Box 10)
- Series VIII: Ceremonials
  - Materials regarding ENEMYWAY. (Published as Origin Legend of the Navaho Enemyway, by Yale University Press, 1938 (Box 11)
  - Nine holograph interlinear notebooks, i.e. #1-5, 7-10 (#6 in holograph interlinear notebook #5 of CHIRICAHUA WINDWAY -- see Box 17. #11 in holograph interlinear notebook #2 of SUCKINGWAY -- see Box 18) (Box 11)
  - Typescripts (original) of songs. Interlinear. Typescripts (original) of notes to text. Holograph corrections. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence regarding publications. 1936-1938. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Materials regarding UPWARD-REACHING WAY. (Published as Emergence Myth, According to the Hanelthnayhe or Upward-Reaching Rite, by the Museum of Navajo Ceremonial Art, 1949. Also published as Upward-Moving and Emergence Way: the Gishin Biye' version, edited by Karl W. Luckert, University of Nebraska Press, 1981). See also Box 28 for additional drafts of the Emergence Myth. 1949, 1981 (Box 11)
  - Typescript (carbon): "Creation and Emergence Myth of the Navaho." Also a typescript and holograph draft. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Typescript (carbon): "Creation and Emergence Myth of the Navaho." Also a typescript and holograph draft (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Typescript (carbon): "The Hanelnehe Boxotco Dji." Also a holograph ms., and holograph notes of ceremony detail. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Original drawings used in the published work. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Materials regarding BEAUTYWAY. (Published as Beautyway: a Navaho Ceremonial, edited by Leland C. Wyman, Pantheon Books). 1957 (Box 12)
  - Five holograph interlinear notebooks. (Box 12)
  - Typescript (carbon) Text and trans. as published, but the notes to both are different. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Materials regarding WATERWAY. (Published as Waterway: a Navaho Ceremonial Myth. Orthography by I.W. Goossen; appendix by Karl W. Luckert, Museum of Northern Arizona Press). 1979 (Box 12)
  - Five holograph interlinear notebooks. (Box 12)
  - Typescript (carbon) of text and trans. with corresponding notes. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Materials regarding BIG GODWAY and DOWNWAY (Box 13)
  - Four holograph notebooks -- some interlinear, but mostly text. (Box 13)
  - Typescript (original and carbon) of text only. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Materials regarding PROSTITUTION WAY and MOTHWAY. (Published as Love-magic and Butterfly People: the Slim Curly version of the Ajilee and Mothway Myths, edited by I.W. Goossen and Karl W. Luckert, Museum of Northern Arizona Press). 1978 (Box 13)
  - Five holograph interlinear notebooks. (Box 13)
  - Typescript (original and carbon) of text and trans. with corresponding notes. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Typescript (original and carbon) of text and trans. with corresponding notes. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Holograph notes and various typescripts of the introduction. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Materials regarding NAVAJO FLINTWAY. (Published as Origin Legend of Navaho Flintway, University of Chicago Press. Version A). 1943 (Box 14)
  - Ten holograph interlinear notebooks. Version A, by Slim Curly of Crystal. 1939-1941 (Box 14)
  - Ten holograph interlinear notebooks. Version B, by Curly Chinlee. 1929-1930 (Box 14)
  - One original drawing for p.23 of published text. (Box 14)
  - Materials regarding MOUNTAIN TOP WAY. (Published as The Mountainway of the Navajo, by Leland C. Wyman, University of Arizona Press, 1975) 1975 (Box 15)
  - Six holograph interlinear notebooks. (Box 15)
  - Typescript (original) of text and transcript with corresponding notes. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Typescript (original) of text and transcript with corresponding notes. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Holograph notes. (p. 43-44 missing) (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of original legend (by ??) (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Materials regarding RED ANTWAY. (Published as The Red Antway of the Navaho, by Leland C. Wyman, Museum of Navaho Ceremonial Art. 1965 (Box 16)
  - Three holograph interlinear notebooks. (Box 16)
  - Holograph notebook of notes. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Typescript (carbon) of text and trans. with accompanying notes. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Typescript (original and carbon) of interlinear copies of songs. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Materials regarding BIG STARWAY (Box 16)
  - Four holograph interlinear notebooks. (Box 16)
  - Typescripts (original) of Liberation Prayer and songs, text and trans. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Three notebooks (interlinear, text of songs, drawings, notes in English). (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Materials regarding NIGHTWAY (Box 16)
  - Holograph notes to a text ? Typescript (carbon) of Liberation Prayer Song. Interlinear. Holograph notebook (part interlinear) of Nightway prayers and songs. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Materials regarding CHIRICAHUA WINDWAY.(Published in The Windways of the Navaho, by Leland C. Wyman, The Taylor Museum of the Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center). Additional notes in notebook for NAVAJO WINDWAY -- See Box 18 1962 (Box 17)
  - Version A, by Slim Curly of Crystal. 1932 (Box 17)
  - Four holograph interlinear noteboks. (Box 17)
  - One holograph book of notes, etc., in English. (Box 17)
  - Preliminary typescript (carbon) (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Preliminary typescript (carbon) (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Final typescript (original), chapters 1-7 only (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Version B, by Salt Water Man of Lukachuckai. 1931 (Box 17)
  - Five holograph interlinear notebooks ( #5 also contains #6 of ENEMYWAY -- see Box 11) (Box 17)
  - Typescripts (carbon) of text and trans. with corresponding notes. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Typescripts (carbon) of text and trans. with corresponding notes. Additional notes in notebook for NAVAJO WINDWAY - See Box 18. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Materials regarding NAVAJO WINDWAY. (Published in The Windways of the Navaho, by Lealand C. Wyman, The Taylor Museum of the Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center). 1962 (Box 18)
  - Eight holograph interlinear notenooks. (Box 18)
  - Two holograph (English) notebooks of notes, etc. (#1 also contains notes for CHIRICAHUA WINDWAY -- see Box 17). (Box 18)
  - Typescript (carbon) of text and trans. with corresponding notes. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Typescript (carbon) of text and trans. with corresponding notes. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Completed typescript (original) -- p. 1-11 only. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous typescript notes, and 2 holograph notebooks. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Materials regarding SUCKINGWAY. (Published by St. Michaels Press, 1950, in Legend of the Ghostway Ritual in the Male Branch of Shootingway ... Suckingway: its Legend and Practice). 1950 (Box 18)
  - Three holograph notebooks: 2 interlinear (#2 contains also #11. p. 588 - 602, of ENEMYWAY -- see Box 11) and 1 of notes in English. (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Typescript (carbon) of trans. and notes. (Box 18)
  - Materials regarding SHOOTINGWAY. (Box 19)
  - Eleven holograph notebooks (some interlinear, some text only) of Blue Eyes and Gray Man versions. (Box 19)
  - Five holograph interlinear notebooks of White Singer version. (Published by University of Chicago Press, 1947, as Prayerstick Cutting in a Five Night Navaho Ceremonial of the Male Branch of Shootingway (Box 19)
  - One holograph notebook (English): "Footnotes to dine'tbahi." (Box 19)
  - Holograph ms. and typescripts of forward, notes, text, and translation of Liberation Prayer. (Box 19)
  - Materials regarding SHOOTINGWAY. (Box 20)
  - Typescript (original) interlinear (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Typescript (original) text -- old orthography, p.1-341. (p.1-113, uncorrected; p.114-341, corrected) (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Typescript (original) text -- new orthography, p.1-350, (p.242-350 published in Legend of the Ghostway Ritual in the Male Branch of Shootingway, St. Michaels Press. 1950 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Typescript (original) trans. p.1-341 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Typescript (original) trans. p.1-341 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Materials regarding BLESSINGWAY. (Published in Blessingway, by Leland C. Wyman, University of Arizona Press. 1970 (Box 21)
  - Version I, by Slim Curly. (Box 21)
  - Ten holograph interlinear notebooks. (Box 21)
  - Three holograph notebooks (English) of footnotes. (Box 21)
  - Correspondence regarding publication. 1927-1969 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence regarding publication. 1927-1969 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence regarding publication. 1927-1969 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence regarding publication. 1927-1969 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Misc. notes by Father Berard. (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Materials regarding BLESSINGWAY. (See publication note for Box 21) (Box 22)
  - Version I, by Slim Curly. (Box 22)
  - Transcript (original) of contents, introductions, index (incomplete), and chapters 1-65 (some missing). Text and trans. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Transcript (original) of contents, introductions, index (incomplete), and chapters 1-65 (some missing). Text and trans (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Transcript (original) of contents, introductions, index (incomplete), and chapters 1-65 (some missing). Text and trans (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Transcript (original) of contents, introductions, index (incomplete), and chapters 1-65 (some missing). Text and trans (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Typescript (original) Navajo text only, p.1-100. (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Page proof, chapters 1-21. (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Materials regarding BLESSINGWAY. (See publication note for Box 21) (Box 23)
  - Version II, by Frank Mitchell and Curly txoaxedlini. (Box 23)
  - Twelve holograph interlinear notebooks, chapters 1-30 (F.M.) (Box 23)
  - Eleven holograph interlinear notebooks, chapters 31-60 (C.t.) (Box 23)
  - One holograph notebook (English) of footnotes. (Box 23)
  - Materials regarding BLESSINGWAY. (See publication note for Box 21) (Box 24)
  - Version II, by Frank Mitchell. (Box 24)
  - Completed transcript: Contents, introd. (2 drafts), chapters 1-30 (original) (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Completed transcript: Contents, introd. (2 drafts), chapters 1-30 (original) (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Completed transcript: Contents, introd. (2 drafts), chapters 1-30 (original) (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Completed transcript: Contents, introd. (2 drafts), chapters 1-30 (original) (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Typescript (original) text and notes, chapters 31-60, p.241-497. (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Typescript (original) trans., p.241-262, 301-427. (p.263-300 and p.428-497 missing) (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Typescript (carbon) notes to trans., p.498-535. (p.536 to end missing) (Box 24)
- Series IX: Reprints Pertaining to the Navajo
  - Various authors, various publications. Includes a few by Father Berard. (Box 25)
- Series X: Navajo Language and Grammar
  - Lessons in Navajo: (Box 26)
  - Three typescript notebooks; holograph notes by Fr. Berard and E. Sapir. (Box 26)
  - Two typescript versions of same subject, different from the above. One mineographed version of same subject, different from above. (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Holograph fragments. (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - "Translation of Lessons in Navajo for Mr. Sandoval," by I. Reade. (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Three holograph notebooks on grammar, vocabulary, etc. (Box 26)
  - "Verbal stem Forms." p.1-380. Typescript (original) (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - "Verbal stem Forms." p.1-380. Typescript (original) (Box 27, Folder 2)